Preliminary Inventory to the James Heyworth-Dunne Papers, 1860-1949
Hoover Institution Archives
James Heyworth-Dunne Papers,
1860-1949
49005
Heyworth-Dunne, James
7 manuscript boxes (2.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Theses, studies, notes, writings, and correspondence, relating to the history, philosophy, literature, education, and religion in Egypt, the Arab world, and Turkey.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Arabic language.; Arabic literature.; Arabic philology.; Civilization, Islamic.; Sociology, Islamic.; Egypt.; Middle East.; Turkey.; Africa
Caveat
The James Heyworth Dunne Collection in the Hoover Institution Archives consists of seven boxes of miscellaneous materials written or gathered by James Heyworth Dunne. The following is a partial listing of the contents of those boxes, based on my inspection of the collection on May 3rd and 5th, 1983. The list is partial because of the great amount of time it would take for a piece by piece enumeration of the contents. One of the peculiarities of the collection is that Heyworth Dunne (henceforward "JHD") tagged individual components with serially-numbered gummed labels. In many cases, the labels were affixed to monographic volumes, some of which were catalogued into the Hoover stack collection and the Hoover Middle East Collection; others of which remain uncatalogued; while still others, monographic in form but not in content, are to be found in the archive. In many other cases, however, the tags were affixed to envelopes of clippings or reproductions, or to individual pages, sheets, documents, photostats, and photographs. In such cases, when one of the boxes or a subdivision of a box contains a number of individually tagged and numbered items, no attempt has been made to identify the items, to list their individual members, nor even to indicate the span of numbers included in that part of the archive.
In all cases in which item numbers are given, the numbers have been recorded after visual inspection of the archive. No attempt was made, however, to verify if envelopes or folders actually contained the numbered items listed on the outside of the containers.
Unless an author is specified, the author or compiler of the materials in the archive is JHD. Titles enclosed within quotation marks are copied as is from the materials in the archive. Illegible words or questionalbe readings are indicated by this writer's use of (?). Statements that works are unpublished were copied as is from the materials in the archive, and may no longer be valid.
Edward A. Jajko
Middle East Bibliographer
5/16/83
Container List
- "Notes on Egypt", 3770-3774 (Box 1)
  5 bound volumes of ms and typed notes on books and articles, all dealing with Egypt and the Middle East
- "Notes on Egypt", 3775-3792 (Box 2)
  - 2 bound volumes of ms and typed notes on books and articles on Egypt and the Middle East, 3775 & 3769
  - 17 notebooks containing ms notes on various subjects, as follows
    Partial title (from cover of notebook)
    - "Muslim civilisation during the Abbasid Period I", 3776
    - "Muslim civilisation during the Abbasid Period II", 3777
    - "Bibliography...", 3778
    - "The Gulistan. 1934.", 3779
    - (No title), 3780
    - "Rifaah's biography...", 3781
    - "Mist...", 3782
    - "Notes on 19th Century Egypt II", 3783
    - "Notes on 19th Century Egypt I", 3784
    - "Notes from Elyas Ayubi", 3785
    - "Notes from Hamont...", 3786
    - "Notes on Jabarti's History...", 3787
    - "Extracts and notes from European works in British Museum", 3788
    - "Statistics from Dor Bey...", 3789
    - "Notes on 19th Century Egypt...", 3790
    - "Sabry + Dor Bey", 3791
    - "Extracts and notes from European works in British Museum", 3792
- S.A.A.A. Khulusy, Shi'ism and its influence on Arabic literature. SOAS, 1947. Unpublished Ph.D. Diss. (JHD ms note), 3796; 287, xxvl leaves, typed, in clamp binder (Box 3)
- JHD?, The Islamic craft gild (sic), with special reference to Persia. Unpublished (JHD ms note) typescript, 3807; 170 loosely sewn leaves, in folder
- JHD ms extracts from A.A. Bevan, The Rise of the Saracens and the foundation of the Western Empire. (Cambridge Medieval History, 1913), 3793; 194 leaves, bound
- El-Rayes, M.D. The concept of the state in Islamic political theory. Unpublished Ph.D. Diss. (JHD ms note), 3795; 211 leaves, bound
- "Notes on Arabic language," ring binder, 3798 (Box 4)
- Western influences in the Arabic literature of Egypt and Syria between 1820 and 1879, (by JHD?), 3812; 212 leaves, typescript
- George Daud Shahla, The Arab conception of the ideal teacher as revealed in Arabic pedagogical literature. Unpublished MA thesis, 3797; 139 leaves, typescript
- Ishaq Musa Husseini, The life and works of Ibn Qutayba. Unpublished Ph.D. thesis, Univ. of London, 1934, 3800; 131 leaves, typescript
- "Notes on Arabic language," JHD ms notes, 3799; +/- 50 leaves
- University of London envelope containing numerous samples of Arabic calligraphy (photos); portion of an Arabic ms; Arabic ms letter or document; all with individual item numbers (Box 5)
- Envelope. Eight photostats of pages from I. Kratschkovsky's Die arabische Poetik im ix. Jahrhundert, 7299
- Envelope 1 leaf photostat of "Allocution...de Mohamed-Bey..." 1846, 3809
- Envelope Photostats of pages of article "Zur arabischen Übersetzung der Poetik des Aristoteles," by Martin Plessner, Orientalische Literaturzeitung, 1981, 7298
- Envelope Twenty-two photostats of pages from G. Bergsträsser, Koranlesung in Kairo, 7296
- More of same, 7297
- Folder. JHD ms "Notes on Egypt", 3808
- Folder. JHD ms "Notes and (?) on Egypt", 3803
- Folder. JHD ms "Notes on Egypt" (from books), 3804
- Folder. JHD ms "Collection of proverbs in Arabic. Manuscript written out for JHD", 3805
- Folder. "Articles on Semitic languages and Arabic", 3806
- Folder. "Photostatic copy of extract from Browning's report to (?)...", 3802
- Folder. "Pellisier's report on Egypt June 1849 - photostatic copy of B.N. Paris original - since lost - This is the only copy in existence, 3801
- Rapport de la mission spéciale en Egypte. 1920? (Great Britain. F.O) Bound, 7026 (Box 6)
- Elyas Ayubi, La Question égyptienne. JHD ms note: unpublished manuscript on modern Egypt. (actually typescript; ms in part only), 7325
- "Egyptian papers of J. Heyworth Dunne," typescript (Folder Envelope)
- JHD's "Proposal for a program of Near and Middle Eastern Studies at the George Washington University.", 7078
- JHD's "Modern education in Saudi Arabia". Unpublished, 7079
- I.Y. Kratchkovsky: "Arabic literature in the twentiety century." Unpublished, 7080
- "The Arab League - a general view of the Arab League during the war between the Jews and the Arabs and the position after the TRUCE," unpublished, 7096
- JHD: "France and Mohamed Ali: 1800-1841 ," unpublished, 7081
- "Egyptian government mission members in America, May 5th, 1948," Ministry of Education, General Administration of Missions, 7083
- JHD: "Notes on modern Arabic (principally Egyptian) literature," 1947, 7082
- Photographs of seals? stamps? "Material collected for a study of the (?) (?) Khairat - J (?) Effendi.", 7318-7323
- JHD: "Notes on B.B.C." Reports by JHD on the need for, and later the effectiveness of, BBC news broadcasts to the Arab World. Includes 1 typescript of "9 transcripts of news bulletins from the B.B.C. Arabic Service when it was first begun." Also newspaper clippings on effectiveness of the broadcasts. Also includes several numbered photographed examples of Arabic calligraphy, and two photographs of Khayrat Efendi. Also 1 small map of pre-WWI Syria/Palestine, 7352-7364
- "31 sheets of notes and translations (?) corrections (?) MacMahon-Sherif Hussein correspondence.", 7335
- marked 7326-7333 but also containing 7334: "Certified copies of the famous MacMahon-Sherif Hussein correspondence". (Arabic) (Folder Envelope)
- Miscellaneous papers on education and oriental studies in England, Russia, Egypt. Reports on SOAS (Box 7, Folder Folder)
- Containing: (Folder Folder)
  - R.N. Broadley: Adventure in Language, (assembled from clippings), 4838
  - JHD: "Notes on the accusative (in Arabic) of the subject after inna and its sisters", 5081
  - "al-Hamasah," typed, 4998-5003
  - JHD: "Printing and translation under Muhammad Ali of Egypt: the foundation of modern Arabic". offprint from JRAS June 1940, 4328
- Containing: (Folder Folder)
  - Miscellaneous JHD papers on language education
  - Four JHD offprints from BSOS
  - Small Arabic ms book, unpublished: Jamiat al-alam min kulli man lahu mayyizah aw maziyah bayna al-inam, Jam Muhammad Kamal al-Din al-Adhami, 4147
  - Unpublished Arabic ms in pencil: Hadha marsum bad al-muluk al-Salajiqah fi ilzam ahl al-riqqah. al-Shurut al-shariyah allati haddadha, Amir al-mu minim Sayyidina Umar ibn al-Khattab ... sanat 755 ..., 4818
  - Arabic ms: Hadhihi majmuah mabsutah min mutafarriqat min majma al-amthal al-ammiyah allati dabajha al-marhum al-Shaykh Hasan al-Alati ..., 4951
- Containing: (Folder Folder)
  - News clippings, 4797
  - Clippings; "The outlook on Egypt," typed, 4903
  - "Twenty-six sheets of notes and references from the Royal Archives in Cairo" (JHD ms), 5575
- Containing: (Folder Folder)
  - Scrapbook clippings from Egyptian Gazette, 5211
  - "Note de Me. Tewfiq Iscarous sur l'Histoire de l'Egypte au Moyen-Age par J.J. Marcel," typed, 4508
  - Envelope. "Various notes written in 1939 in (?) Egypt.", 4444
  - Special section of Manchester Guardian Commercial, April 1, 1938, on Arab world, 4357
- Containing: (Folder Folder)
  - Middle East map; Night club (?) programs or souvenirs?, 4960
  - Plan of S.S. El Nil; programs and souvenirs of Société Misr de Navigation Maritime; other miscellaneous small papers, 4157